Mari Sandoz Collection
Mari Sandoz Collection
1935-1965
Sandoz, Mari, 1896-1966.
1.0 linear ft.
Papers of the American novelist, chronicler of pioneer and Native American life on the Nebraska plains. Correspondence (1935-1950), principally with Atlantic Monthly Press editor Paul Hoffman; typescript drafts and revisions of an article, a book, These Were the Sioux, and two essays; and galley proofs.
149562
Biographical History
Mari Susette Sandoz (1896-1966) was an American novelist and chronicler of pioneer and Indian life on the Nebraska Plains. Born on the Sandoz homestead in northwestern Nebraska, Sandoz was the eldest daughter of Swiss immigrant parents Jules Ami and Mary Elizabeth (Fehr) Sandoz. She started school at nine and wrote her first story shortly thereafter. She taught in country schools, attended business college, and at intervals between 1922 and 1931 studied at the University of Nebraska, supporting herself with part-time and full-time jobs, including research on the Sioux and other work for the Nebraska State Historical Society.
In 1935 the publication of Old Jules, a biography of her pioneer father, established her as an important writer on the American West and won the Atlantic Monthly prize. Her second book, the novel Slogum House, was published in 1937. From 1943 until the 1960s Sandoz spent half her time in New York City, returning to Nebraska to gather material for her writing.
Besides numerous short stories and magazine contributions, Mari Sandoz wrote Love Song to the Plains (1961), Old Jules Country (1965), and These Were the Sioux (1961). Her novels include The Tom-Walker (1947), Winter Thunder (1954), The Horsecatcher (1957), and Son of the Gamblin' Man (1960). In 1964 the publication of The Beaver Men marked the completion of her Great Plains series (previous titles in the series were Crazy Horse, Cheyenne Autumn, The Buffalo Hunters, The Cattlemen, and Old Jules).
For further biographical information, see the "Autobiographical sketch of Mari Sandoz' early years" in Hostiles and Friendlies: Selected Short Writings of Mari Sandoz (Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1959)
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Mari Sandoz Collection is divided into correspondence and writings.
Correspondence contains both incoming and outgoing letters; the bulk consists of 24 letters from Mari Sandoz to Paul Gerhard Hoffman of the Atlantic Monthly Press, written between 1935 and 1938. Hoffman was Sandoz' editor for Old Jules, Slogum House, Capital City, Crazy Horse, and The Horsecatcher. With the letter of 3 Dec 1935 are two letters (24 May 1900 and 3 Nov 1907) from her father Jules Ami Sandoz and one letter (20 Dec 1893, Zurich) from Rosalie Epprecht to Jules Sandoz. Enclosed with the letter of 11 Dec 1935 is an undated letter from Mamie Meredith to Mari Sandoz. Letters of 15 Oct 1935 and 10 Oct 1937 include snapshots of Mari Sandoz. There is one incoming letter (24 May 1950) from Helen Hector, associate editor of Reader's Digest, in two copies.
Writings contains manuscripts and production material for work dating from the late 1950s to 1965. Besides typescripts for three short pieces, there are manuscripts of production material for three books: The Cattlemen, Old Jules Country, and These Were the Sioux. The latter title is the most heavily represented, with typescripts in four stages of revision and both galley and page proofs.
Arrangement of the Collection
Letters are arranged chronologically. Writings are arranged alphabetically by type and within that by title.
Related Material
See also the
Felie Woodrow Clark Thesis
, which contains biographical and bibliographical material about Sandoz.
Subject and Genre Headings
Literature -- American Fiction; Women Authors; Hoffman, Paul.; Sandoz, Mari, 1896-1966.; These were the Sioux.; American fiction -- West (U.S.); Dakota Indians.; Western stories.; Women authors, American.; Women novelists, American.; West (U.S.) -- In literature.; Correspondence.; Galley proofs.; Manuscripts for publication.; Authors.; Novelists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Manuscripts and production material of These Were the Sioux, gift of Mari S. Sandoz, 1962. All other material gifts of James F. Carr, 1960 and 1967.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Hoffman, Paul, 1935-1938; 25 items (Box 1)
    1935 - Jul 10, Jul 16, Jul 17
    1935 - Aug 3, Aug 24
    1935 - Sep 18
    1935 - Oct 15 (photograph enclosed), Oct 15, Oct 31
    1935 - Dec 2 (telegram), Dec 3 (with 3 enclosed letters), Dec 11
    1936 - Mar 4
    1936 - Jul 10
    1936 - Sep 24, Sep 26
    1936 - Dec 16
    1937 - Sep 22
    1937 - Oct 10 (photograph enclosed)
    1937 - Nov 26
    1937 - Dec 7
    1937 - Dec 15
    1938 - Jan 22
    1938 - Apr 12
    1950 - May 24
- Writings
  - Articles
    - "What the Sioux Taught Me", 1960; typescript (Box 1)
  - Books
    - The Cattlemen
      - Corrected galley proofs (Box 1)
      - Page proofs (Box 1)
    - Old Jules Country
      - Page proofs (Box 1)
    - These Were the Sioux
      - First revisions, undated; typescript, revised (Box 2)
      - Second revisions, undated; typescript, revised (Box 2)
      - Second manuscript, 1961; typescript copy, revised (Box 2)
      - Second castoffs, undated; typescript, revised (Box 2)
      - Front matter copy and layout (Box 2)
      - Master galley proofs (Box 2)
      - Author's page proofs of front matter (Box 2)
      - Author's page proofs (Box 2)
      - Author's corrected page proofs of front matter, pp. 1-13 (Box 2)
      - Publisher's corrected page proofs (Box 3)
      - Signatures, unbound (Box 3)
  - Essays
    - Introduction to The Cheyenne Indians by George Bird Grinnell (1962), Jul 1962; typescript, revised (Box 3)
    - "Some thoughts on the origins and the writing of Son of the Gamblin' Man", Aug 1960; typescript copy (Box 3)